Guide to the African American Jazz Preservation Society of Pittsburgh Oral History Project Records and Recordings, 1995-1999 AIS.1998.04
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Transcripts, 1995-1999; II.
  - Gambrell, Jacques "Bill" interviewed by Charles E. Austin, May 8, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    [T1S1] History of Local 471; Local 471 politics; performing in Pittsburgh; racism on the job; Union pensions; involvement in the Union; performing in high school. [T1S2] Performing in Pittsburgh; racism at the Moose; Union pensions and gold cards; Union merger and politics; importance of professionalism, appearance, and adapting to the audience.
  - Hardy, Rubye Younge interviewed by Charles E. Austin, December 10, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Hardy, Ruby Younge, a piano and organ player who performed in Pittsburgh clubs and Ebenezer Church.
    [T1S1] Childhood and playing music; joining Local 471 and Musicians' Club; trio and booking jobs; other musicians; being Local 471's secretary; record keeping and Union merge; performing in downtown Pittsburgh; performing with Honeyboy Minor; race relations in downtown clubs.
    [T1S2] Other musicians; education; importance of reading music; Local 471 officer politics; teaching music; performing in church; other musicians; Union merge politics; musician friends; problems after Union merge; transcription jobs.
  - Harper, Walt interviewed by Charles E. Austin, July 21, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Harper, Walt, a pianist and bandleader who performed in Pittsburgh and owned two clubs (Attic and Harper's).
    [T1S1] Musical family and beginning music; early jobs and traveling; racism; composing music; relationship with Local 471 and members; Musicians' Club camaraderie; club ownership; tearing down Hill District for Civic Arena; Bamboola; camaraderie in Hill District.
    [T1S2] Musicians' Club and moving to East Liberty; importance of reading music; being a bandleader; group dynamics; advice to younger musicians.
  - Harris, Joseph interviewed by Charles E. Austin, December 6, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Harris, Joseph (December 6, 1995), a drummer who performed in Pittsburgh, around the United States and in Europe.
    [T1S1] Playing and performing in high school; time in the Army; balancing club, school and steel mill work; private lessons; Pittsburgh clubs; Local 471; Union merger.
    [T1S2] Racism; driving home from gigs; camaraderie in old Musicians' Club; problem with Union member; inspirational musicians; Local 471 camaraderie; importance of day job; advice for younger musicians.
  - Harris, Joseph Jr. interviewed by Charles E. Austin, August 7, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Harris, Joseph Jr. (August 7, 1998), a drummer who performed in Pittsburgh, around the United States and in Europe.
    [T1S1] Beginning music and playing in Pittsburgh; performing in Chicago; traveling around the United States; performing in Europe; Local 471 musicians and camaraderie; high school music programs; music proving a fulfilling life; other musicians; performing and learning in Pittsburgh.
    [T1S2] Family; private lessons; importance of reading; changes in music; Union merge politics; race relations; time in Sweden; importance of being prepared and self image; problems after Union merge; golf.
  - Henderson, Pete interviewed by Charles E. Austin, March 8, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Henderson, Pete, a trumpeter who played in the Service, toured with Pearl Bailey, and played in Pittsburgh.
    [T1S1] Acquiring a trumpet and private lessons; high school jazz ensemble; time in the Service; performing in his youth; camaraderie of the Union; tour with Pearl Bailey; playing in Pittsburgh clubs.
    [T1S2] Racial discrimination at Volkiens; musical influences; changes in jazz; effects of losing old Club; the Pittsburgh sound; Union merger; boat touring; teaching music; advice for younger musicians.
  - Hill, Herman interviewed by Charles E. Austin, September 23, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Hill, Herman, a trombone and baritone horn player who performed in Pittsburgh and New York and worked for the Courier and the New York Times.
    [T1S1] High school and joining union; Local 802 (New York); Navy; Local 471; moving to New York; Local 471 members and Musicians' Club; private lessons; Navy responsibilities; childhood memories; touring; Pittsburgh clubs; integration from merger.
    [T1S2] Union merger and tensions; history of Musicians' Club; returning from New York after merger; childhood inspirations; playing for Mellon's Band; musical style and importance of doubling; other musicians; Charles's (interviewer) jobs after merger; advice to younger musicians.
  - Hughes, John interviewed by Ms. Yamu, April 4, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Hughes, John, (April 4, 1996), a piano player who performed in Pittsburgh and was also a teacher.
    [T1S1] Beginning music and family; joining Local 471; about Local 471; other jobs; Pittsburgh clubs; teaching and performing; jazz and Pittsburgh; writing music; staying in Pittsburgh and relationship with traveling musicians; WPA band history; old Musicians' Club; Local 471 officers; education and performing.
    [T1S2] Differences between Musicians' Clubs; difference between Local 60 and Local 471; preparing to perform; other musicians; advice to younger musicians.
  - Hughes, John interviewed by Ms. Yamu, May 25, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Hughes, John, (May 25, 1996), a piano player who performed in Pittsburgh and was also a teacher.
    [T1S1] Education; interest in music; significance of jazz; favorite music; first professional job; private clubs versus public locations; current Pittsburgh clubs; importance of practicing.
  - Humphries, Lawrence interviewed by Charles E. Austin, July 8, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Humphries, Lawrence, a tenor saxophone and clarinet player who composed music and performed in Pittsburgh.
    [T1S1] Musical family and childhood; playing in Pittsburgh; uncles' influence and musicians' legacy; performers in Pittsburgh; uncles in New York; composing music; brother Roger; time in New York; family; Local 471.
    [T1S2] Enlisting in the Air Force; moving to New York; studying music; doubling; advice to younger musicians; Charles's (interviewer) working after Union merger; importance of studying music; family responsibilities.
  - Humphries, Roger interviewed by Charles E. Austin, August 8, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Humphries, Roger, a drummer who began performing at a young age, toured and performed in Pittsburgh.
    [T1S1] Musical family and childhood; family inspiration; camaraderie with older musicians; purpose of JPS oral histories; rehearsal bands and teaching music; East Liberty Club; performing in Pittsburgh; drum playing style; Pittsburgh's notoriety; importance of education and a job; enjoyment from performing.
    [T1S2] Union merger court case; merger tensions; quitting the Union; inspirational drummers; advice to younger musicians.
  - Jones, Roy interviewed by Charles E. Austin, March 12, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Jones, Roy, a trumpet player who performed the National Guard Band and in Pittsburgh with the Fitzpatrick brothers.
    [T1S1] Music in high school; National Guard Band; the Fitzpatrick brothers and joining Local 471; performing, arranging and learning; old Musicians' Club camaraderie; clubs on the Northside; quitting playing; inspirational musicians; advice to younger musicians; clubs and musicians.
    [T1S2] Camaraderie and maintaining relationships with musicians; benefits of learning an instrument; difficulties of aging and performing; performing and adapting to individual clubs; camaraderie in black neighborhoods of Pittsburgh; music as an escape; younger generation.
  - Kelly, Marcus interviewed by Charles E. Austin, April 16, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Kelly, Marcus, a bass player who was a bandleader and performed in Pittsburgh.\
    [T1S1] Pay scale; beginning music; Army; Local 471; traveling; bands; Pittsburgh clubs; musicians and substance abuse; being a bandleader.
    [T1S2] Being a bandleader; Musicians' Club, members and history; teaching music; pensions and insurance; younger musicians; Local 471 camaraderie; importance of reading music.
  - Kemp, Jesse interviewed by Cathy Cairns, December 15, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Kemp, Jesse, a pianist and percussionist who was exposed to jazz by his older brother DeRuyter "Ducky" Kemp, performed jazz and Christian music in Pittsburgh and participated in opposition to the Union merger.
    [T1S1] Music and childhood; inspiration; exposure to jazz and union through brother; time in army and post office; re-interest in jazz scene; playing at Pittsburgh clubs; studying at the University of Pittsburgh; Christian education; changes in jazz; involvement in Christian music. [T1S2] Opposition to Union merger; advice to younger musicians.
  - Kennedy, Joe Jr. interviewed by himself, September 1998 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Kennedy, Joe Jr., a violinist who performed in Pittsburgh as a youth, performed for the Army and Richmond Symphony, and toured internationally.
    [T1S1] Childhood and musical family; studying music; time in army band; Musicians' Club and union members; touring with Four Strings; Richmond Symphony; international touring; university positions; esteemed Local 471 members.
  - Laley, Daniel interviewed by Charles E. Austin, November 2, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Laley, Dan, a bass player who performed in Pittsburgh and around the United States.
    [T1S1] Beginning music; touring; Army; band members; musicians.
    [T1S2] Importance of being versatile; gifts of musical career; jam sessions; importance of touring; performing with great musicians.
  - Lee, Dave interviewed by Charles E. Austin, March 6, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Lee, David, a percussionist who learned from experience with jazz musicians, worked during the day and performed at Pittsburgh clubs at night.
    [T1S1] Learning from musicians; musicians'' appearance; time in the Navy; Union members; ballgames and volunteering; politics with touring; playing at Pittsburgh clubs; Union members.
    [T1S2] Musicians' pensions; burden of heavy instruments; advice to younger musicians; reading music; role models.
  - Lee, Harold interviewed by Charles E. Austin, July 3, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Lee, Harold, a percussionist and fifty year Union member who began playing in the 40s in the Pittsburgh area, traveled with the Navy Band until 1946 when he returned and continued to perform in the Pittsburgh area. [T1S1] First performance; participation in Langley High School band; private lessons; traveling with the Navy Band; playing at Pittsburgh clubs; the Union clique; the Club; younger musicians; reading music; mechanical vs. natural musicianship; the theater circuit; expected price for performances; childhood inspiration; performing with the Carnival.
    [T1S2] Children's participation in music; the WPA band; MPT funds; Local 471 officers; the Union merger; advice to younger musicians; Union inclusion of African American musicians in publicized performances; gospel music; biographical information; fifty year card.
  - McCown, Frank interviewed by Charles E. Austin, July 16, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    McCown, Frank, a saxophone player who was a bandleader and performed in Pittsburgh.
    [T1S1] High school band; Navy; private lessons; being a bandleader; college; Local 471 Big Band; Musicians' Club relocation; performing with other bands; being band leader; Union dues; musicians.
    [T1S2] Recording music; booking gigs; territory bands; Union merge politics; advice to younger musicians; rehearsal bands.
  - McDaniel, Tommy interviewed by Charles E. Austin, March 9, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    McDaniel, Tommy, a bass player who performed in Pittsburgh.
    [T1S1] Music and high school; joining Local 471 and Union members; family; Pittsburgh clubs; importance of reading and writing music; Union merger; hopes of continuing jazz tradition; results of Union merger; significance of Pittsburgh jazz; performing in Pittsburgh; pension program; inspirational performers; reputation of Pittsburgh performers.
    [T1S2] Other musicians; quitting performing; Los Angeles performers; power of music; advice to younger musicians; impressions of Musicians' Club and Union; great musicians.
  - McKay, Delsey interviewed by Cathy Cairns, March 31, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    McKay, Delsey, a pianist and contortionist who had a popular variety act in Pittsburgh for over twenty years, studied at Julliard, toured Europe, and conducted historical research.
    [T1S1] Musical family and childhood; high school activities; amateur hour; beginning show business; unique variety act; surgery and invention of coat hanger act; performing piano; joining Local 60; joining Local 471; racism and moving to Hill District; Lonnie Fisher's death; performing in Oakland; band leader.
    [T1S2] Studying at Duquesne University; New York City and studying at Julliard; London and recordings; death of Martin Luther King Jr.; competing in international music festivals; involvement with American Bicentennial Artists' Day; history of Ben Banaka; Banaka's grandmother's life in England.
    [T2S1] Banaka family's history in U.S.; importance of representation in Washington D.C.; McKay's family's involvement in Civil War; hope that Washington D.C. becomes state.
  - McMahon, William "Bass" interviewed by Charles E. Austin, August 24, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    McMahon, Bass, a bass player who performed in Pittsburgh and around the United States.
    [T1S1] Early bands and musicians; joining Local 471; touring and performing with bands; great performers; importance of traveling; current musician relationship; plan for reunion; bands; importance of reading music; loss of musician camaraderie.
    [T1S2] Generational differences.
  - Moody, Willis interviewed by Charles E. Austin, August 22, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Moody, Willis, a drummer who performed in Pittsburgh.
    [T1S1] Army; audition test and joining Local 471; Local 471 Big Band; performing in Pittsburgh; traveling; old Musicians' Club; transcription jobs; playing downtown; Local 471 camaraderie; moving club to East Liberty; Union merger politics; racism in Miami.
    [T1S2] High school band and lessons; Local 471 members.
  - Murphy, Carl interviewed by Charles E. Austin, August 5, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Murphy, Carl, a drummer who performed in Pittsburgh.
    [T1S1] Musical family and beginning music; Army; joining Local 471; differences between Musicians' Clubs; being a bandleader; paying dues; listen to others and learning to read music; bands; musician camaraderie; Local 60 social club and merger politics.
    [T1S2] Union merger politics; Union meetings; effect of the merge; jobs and experience; advice to younger musicians; musicians; similar Union merges; importance of racial heterogeneous musical groups.
  - Nance, Art interviewed by Charles E. Austin, October 5, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Nance, Art, a saxophone player who played in the Army, performed with Walt Harper's Band and was band leader of Art Nance and the Five Deuces.
    [T1S1] Childhood and father's musical inspiration; performing in high school; performing in Army; joining Local 471 and advice from older musicians; joining the Army.
    [T1S2] Performing with Walt Harper and Joe Westray; Union merger politics; advice to younger musicians; musical inspiration.
  - Nelson, Frank interviewed by Charles E. Austin, July 26, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Nelson, Frank, a saxophone player who performed in Pittsburgh with the Silvertones and later with the Bach Choir.
    [T1S1] Beginning music; Local 471 Big Band; performing in Pittsburgh; loss of teeth and ending music career; high school band; Silvertones; audition test and joining Local 471; uncle Norman Ball and musical inspiration; working in a music store; Big Band members.
    [T1S2] Local 471 members and history; advice to younger musicians; singing with Bach Choir.
  - Odum, Joe interviewed by Charles E. Austin, September 17, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Odum, Joe, a drummer who performed in Pittsburgh.
    [T1S1] Studying music; joining the union; performing at Pittsburgh clubs; changes in music; Union merge and importance of staying in Union; transcription and MTP jobs; vaudeville style performers; value of recording jazz history.
    [T1S2] Charles's (interviewer) childhood memories; advice to younger musicians.
  - Patton, Joe interviewed by Charles E. Austin, July 25, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Patton, Joe, a trumpet player who performed in Pittsburgh and played in the Navy.
    [T1S1]Childhood and lessons; joining Local 471; playing in Pittsburgh; Elks clubs; work, school and performing; carnivals; Local 471 officers; musicians and photograph.
    [T1S2] Other musicians; practicing; advice to younger generation.
  - Payne, James interviewed by Charles E. Austin, July31, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Payne, James, a trumpet and piano player who performed for Elks bands and dance clubs, and arranged music.
    [T1S1] Childhood in Uniontown; joining Local 471; beginning music; studying piano and arranging; Elks clubs; old Musicians' Club; participation in Local 471; musicians in Elks Band; musical influence; other musicians; advice to younger musicians.
  - Pryor, Fred interviewed by Charles E. Austin, July 29, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Pyror, Fred, a drummer and band leader who performed in Pittsburgh.
    [T1S1] Playing in high school; clubs in East Liberty; performing in Pittsburgh; other musicians; cabarets.
    [T1S2] Country clubs and formal events; contracts; Union merger; difference after merge; advice to younger musicians; importance of reading; MPT jobs; recording; Local 471 presidents.
  - Smith, Eldridge interviewed by Charles E. Austin, July 10, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Smith, Elderidge, a baritone horn player who performed in the Army, Baltimore and Pittsburgh.
    [T1S1]Playing in high school; joining the Army; Union and fifty year card; Army; performing in Pittsburgh; other musicians; concert bands; MTP jobs; black theater circuit; racism in South; clubs in Pittsburgh; alcohol abuse; other musicians.
    [T1S2] Inspirational musicians; reputations; friendships made while traveling; family and day job; advice to younger musicians; Union merger politics; payment for performances; band bar tabs.
  - Spaulding, George Duke interviewed by Charles E. Austin, October 2, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Spalding, George Duke, a piano player who grew up in the south, studied a Julliard and performed in Pittsburgh.
    [T1S1] Musical family and childhood; joining the union; performing in Pittsburgh; studying at Julliard; performing with white band; performance attire; territory band touring; Union earnings and pensions; importance of day job.
    [T1S2] Local 471 charter; appearance and jobs; Atlantic City; old Musicians' Club; Union merger; advice to younger musicians; performing for religious institutions; future of music.
  - Steath, Ollie interviewed by Charles E. Austin, July 19, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Steath, Ollie, a musician who performed in Pittsburgh.
    [T1S1] Beginning music; performing with group and concert band; Musicians' Club; Elks Band; father's life and musical career; transcription jobs; Union merger and quitting playing; Musicians' Club; importance of preserving jazz history; advice to younger musicians.
  - Thomas, John interviewed by Charles E. Austin, May 27, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Thomas, John, a piano player who played with the Army and traveled to Europe, and performed in Pittsburgh.
    [T1S1] Beginning music; time in Aliquippa; performing in Pittsburgh; time in Army; Local 471 members; day jobs; Pittsburgh clubs and performers; studying at Phileon Music Institute; importance of reading music; other pianists; problems with band members; pension program and responsibilities of bandleaders; treatment of musicians; older Local 471 members.
    [T1S2] Mabel Rogers; the Musicians' Club move; Union merge; MTP jobs; young musicians; being a bandleader; childhood music inspiration; job offer from New York.
  - Thompson, George interviewed by Charles E. Austin, Feburary 23, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Thompson, George (Feburary 23, 1996), an alto and tenor saxophone player who played with Army band and was a member of the Bobby Jones Trio for twenty eight years in Pittsburgh.
    [T1S1] Beginning music and high school band; Army band; joining Local 471; Musicians' Club and jam sessions; Big Band members; expectations from Union merge; band members; loss of camaraderie; merge politics; importance of other job; younger musicians; touring.
    [T1S2] (Distorted discussion); playing to the audience; Elks Band; other musicians; Local 471 clique; other musicians; younger musicians and rehearsal bands.
  - Thompson, George interviewed by Cathy Cairns, December 3, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Thompson, George (December 3, 1997), an alto and tenor saxophone player who played with Army band and was a member of the Bobby Jones Trio for twenty eight years in Pittsburgh.
    [T1S1] Musical family and childhood; Army; early bands and traveling; Bobby Jones Trio; R House and other clubs; musical inspiration; Bobby Jones Trio's cohesiveness; advice to younger musicians; relationship with Union and club; memorable moments; legacy for younger generation.
  - Turrentine, Stanley interviewed by Charles E. Austin, November 23, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Turrentine, Stanley, a saxophone player who began performing at a young age, performed in Pittsburgh, around the United States, and in Europe.
    [T1S1] Musical family and childhood; playing professionally; learning from musicians; touring with Max Roach's band; brother Tommy Turrentine's influence; importance of Musicians' Club; changes in music; touring; expression through music; New York; Tommy's support; advice to younger musicians.
    [T1S2] Other musicians; changes in music; significance of jazz history; AAJPSP Oral Histories Project.
  - Webster, Robin interviewed by Charles E. Austin, September 25, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Webster, Robin, a saxophone player who played for the Army band and in Pittsburgh.
    [T1S1] Childhood and music; Army band; performing in Pittsburgh and other musicians; proper payment for job; rehearsal bands; loss of camaraderie without old Musicians' Club; importance of professionalism and respecting elder musicians; other musicians; performing solo and with trios; mentors from Local 471.
    [T1S2] Intimidation of other players; importance of dedication and practicing; Pittsburgh style of playing; studying music; advice to younger musicians; Union merger; choosing gigs.
  - Westray, Joe interviewed by Charles E. Austin, November 13, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Westray, Joe, by Cathy (sister), a guitarist who was a band leader and Local 471 Union president, and owned a club in Pittsburgh.
    [T1S1] Beginning music and lessons; Local 471 and Musicians' Club; arranging music; touring; playing in Pittsburgh; significance of Joe Westray's Band; other musicians; performance attire; band leader; education; traveling locally with Joe; balancing business and music; Joe's legacy; starting a music school.
    [T1S2] Joe's dream of a music school; Cathy's relationship with Joe; importance of training; Joe's grandson, Ronnie; Musicians' Club relocation; Union Merger and effects; importance of Old Musicians' Club; other musicians.
  - Young, Curtis interviewed by Charles E. Austin, June 9, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Young, Curtis, (June 9, 1995), a drummer who performed in Pittsburgh discusses early history of Local 471.
    [T1S1] History of early union; clubs in the Hill District; Local 471 politics; Union merger politics; importance of historical documents; playing during Great Depression; Local 471 charter; other Pittsburgh musicians.